Guide to the Betsy Wade Files on the Coalition of Labor Union Women WAG.020
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Betsy Wade Files on the Coalition of Labor Union Women
1972-1982
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Wade, Betsy
WAG.020
0.75 Linear Feet in two manuscript boxes.
Betsy Wade, a journalist who worked for many years for the New York Times and a member of the Newspaper Guild of New York, Local 3, was a founding member of New York Trade Union Women and of the Coalition of Labor Union Women (CLUW). The collection consists of correspondence between Wade and other leaders of CLUW, as well as material concerning CLUW conferences and conventions. Administrative materials relating to the New York City Chapter of CLUW (formerly New York Trade Union Women), are also present in the collection, as are clippings and subject files documenting CLUW's efforts on behalf of working women.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Betsy Wade, a journalist and active member of the Newspaper Guild of New York, Local 3, was a founding member of New York Trade Union Women and of the Coalition of Labor Union Women (CLUW).
In the Fall of 1972, the Women's Studies Institute of Cornell University, in collaboration with the Region II Women's Bureau of the U.S. Department of Labor, held a meeting of labor union staff meetings to discuss issues concerning the role of women in unions. This group, which became known as New York Trade Union Women, began to meet monthly for "brown bag" lunches, and called the first New York Trade Union Women's Conference in January 1974.
CLUW was founded in March 1974 in Chicago, adopting four basic goals of action: to promote affirmative action in the workplace; to strengthen the role of women in unions; to organize unorganized women workers; and to increase the involvement of women in the political and legislative process. In 1975, New York Trade Union Women became the New York City chapter of CLUW.
With members from 60 international and national unions across the U.S. and Canada, CLUW currently has an active network of more than 75 chapters.
Sources:
Coalition of Labor Women. "About CLUW." 11 August 2008. http://www.cluw.org/about.html.
Roth, Silke. Building Movement Bridges: The Coalition of Labor Union Women. Westport, CT: Praeger, 2003.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of correspondence between Wade and other leaders of CLUW, including Marjorie Stern, Pat Strandt and Luella Hansberry, as well as material relating to CLUW conferences and conventions. Administrative materials relating to the New York City Chapter of CLUW, including by-laws, election materials, newsletters, reports, resolutions and statements are also present in the collection. Also included are clippings and subject files documenting CLUW's efforts on behalf of working women, including material on the Equal Rights Amendment (1980), the Senatorial campaign of Bella Abzug (1976) and Mary Anne Krupsak's campaign for Lieutenant Governor of New York (1974).
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 1 series:
Missing Title
I, General Files, 1972-1982.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Newspaper Guild of New York: Betsy Wade Files (Wagner #45)
Betsy Wade Photographs (Photos #40)
Newspaper Guild of New York Records (Wagner #125)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Betsy Wade, 1982. The accession number associated with this gift is 1982.001.
Fliers (printed matter); Newsletters.; New York (N.Y.); Clippings (information artifacts); Brochures.; Correspondence.; Women labor union members -- New York (State) -- New York; Women in the labor movement |z United States.; Women labor union members |x Societies, etc.; Coalition of Labor Union Women (U.S.); Coalition of Labor Union Women (U.S.). New York City Chapter; New York Trade Union Women; Krupsak, Mary Anne; Stern, Marjorie.; Strandt, Pat.; Abzug, Bella S., 1920-1998; Wade, Betsy
- Series I: General Files, 1972-1982.
  - Annual Awards Dinner-Dance, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - By-Laws, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - CLUW-IN(newsletter), 1974-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - CLUW News(newsletter), 1975-1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Conferences: Coalition of Labor Union Women Regional Conference (New York, NY), 1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Conferences: First New York Trade Union Women's Conference (New York, NY), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Conferences: "Pay Equity: Issue for the 80's" (New York, NY), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Convention (Coalition of Labor Union Women), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Convention (Coalition of Labor Union Women), 1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Convention (Coalition of Labor Union Women), 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Convention (Coalition of Labor Union Women), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Convention (Coalition of Labor Union Women), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Coalition of Labor Union Women, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Coalition of Labor Union Women, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Coalition of Labor Union Women, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Coalition of Labor Union Women, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: New York City Chapter, Coalition of Labor Union Women, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: New York City Chapter, Coalition of Labor Union Women, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: New York Trade Union Women's Conference, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Elections (Coalition of Labor Union Women), 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Equal Rights Amendment: March on Richmond, VA, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Legislation, 1975-1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Membership Lists and Biographies, 1975-1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Membership Meetings, 1974-1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - National Coordinating Committee (Coalition of Labor Union Women), 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Publicity Materials (Coalition of Labor Union Women), 1974-1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Reports, Resolutions and Statements, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Senator Krupsak for Lieutenant Governor Committee, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Steering Committee (Coalition of Labor Union Women), 1975 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Union Women for Bella Abzug, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 13)